Finding Aid for O’Brien Family (Detroit, Mich.) papers, ca. 1932-1965
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
O’Brien Family (Detroit, Mich.) papers ca. 1932-1965
O’Brien Family
1 linear foot and 1 oversize volume
85401 Aa 2; AC
O'Brien family of northern Michigan and Detroit, Michigan; family papers of Patrick H. O'Brien and other family members.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mr. and Mrs. John O’Brien (donor no. 6526 ) and came to the library in 1980.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Patrick H. O'Brien was born in Michigan's Upper Peninsula on March 15, 1868. He graduated from Northern Indiana Law School in 1891, then began the practice of law in Wisconsin. He moved to Calumet, Michigan in 1899 where he entered private practice and local politics. In 1922, he settled in Detroit where he continued his law and Democratic party activities. He was a candidate for governor in 1932, but was defeated for the nomination; he was, however, elected state attorney general in the fall election. He served one term. In 1937, O'Brien was an unsuccessful candidate for mayor of Detroit. In 1939, he was elected Wayne county probate judge, serving until his retirement in 1956. He died July 27, 1959.
Michael O'Brien, brother of Patrick H. O'Brien, was a Detroit insurance executive with the American Life Insurance Company.
Gerald K. O'Brien, son of Patrick H. O'Brien, served as deputy attorney general of Michigan (1933-1934), assistant prosecutor for Wayne County, 1934-1940, and later Wayne County prosecutor.
John H. O'Brien, son of Michael O'Brien, was a Detroit journalist, working with the Detroit Times and the Detroit News. During the 1950s, O'Brien was executive director of the Hearst newspaper organization's campaign for national highway improvement.
The O'Brien family collection includes papers and scrapbooks of John H. O'Brien, a newsman with the Hearst newspaper chain largely concerning the campaign, 1952-1957, for better interstate highway system. In addition, there are scrapbooks and other materials of Michael O'Brien relating to his insurance business and to the political campaigns of his brother, Patrick H. O'Brien. The papers of Eleanor Lawton O'Brien concern her interests in family planning. The reminiscences of Jean Worth relate to his boyhood in Menominee, Michigan, ca. 1915.
Subjects:
Detroit (Mich.).; Menominee (Mich.).; Women--Michigan--Detroit.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.); American newspapers.; O'Brien family.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
O'Brien, Gerald.; O'Brien, Patrick Henry, 1868-; O'Brien family.
Contributors:
O'Brien, Eleanor Lawton.; O'Brien, John H.; O'Brien, Michael.; O'Brien, Patrick Henry, 1868-; Worth, Jean, 1904-1987.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Family papers
  - Patrick H. O'Brien
    - Miscellaneous clippings and political matter (Box 1)
    - Campaign literature, Detroit mayoral election, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Gerald K. O'Brien (son of Patrick)
    - Clippings and memorabilia (Box 1)
  - Michael O'Brien (brother of Patrick)
    - Clippings and biographical material (Box 1)
    - Scrapbook concerning in part political career of Patrick H. O'Brien, 1932-1936 (Box 1)
    - Scrapbook largely containing advertising publicity for his insurance firm, 1932-1937 (Box 1)
  - John H. O'Brien (son of Michael)
    - Detroit Times miscellanea (Box 1)
    - Scrapbook concerning campaign for better highways, 1952-1957 (Box 1)
      (oversize volume)
    - Scrapbook concerning campaign for better highways, 1955-1956 (Box 1)
      (volume was intended as entry in the Ted V. Rodgers annual journalism awards prize)
    - Miscellanea re. good roads campaign (Box 1)
  - Eleanor (Lawton) O'Brien
    - Legislative work for family planning clinics in Michigan, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Jean Worth
    - Reminiscences of boyhood in Menominee, Michigan, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Photographs of Gerald and Patrick O'Brien (Box 1)